Register of the Joseph Conard and Josephine Whitney Duveneck collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph Conard and Josephine Whitney Duveneck collection
1940-1946
XX032
Conard, Joseph, collector.
5 manuscript boxes 2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Pamphlets, reprints, newsletters, clippings, reports, letters, and notes, relating to conditions in the Japanese relocation camps in the United States during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the Hoover Institution by Mr. Joseph Conard and Mrs. F.S. Duveneck of the American Friends Service Committee, San Francisco.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Pamphlets, reprints, newsletters, clippings, reports, letters, and notes, relating to conditions in the Japanese relocation camps in the United States during World War II.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; Duveneck, Josephine Whitney, 1891-
Collection Contents
- Newsletters of various organizations concerned with justice for Japanese Americans (Box 1)
  [The quality of these materials varies widely from the excellent Resettlement Bulletin of the Committee on Resettlement of Japanese Americans to the Pastoral Letter which is of dubious value as research material.]
  - Penn Notes, April, 1946 (File 1)
  - Japanese-American Committee for Democracy Newsletter, July 1944 - August 1946 (File 1)
  - Committee on Resettlement of Japanese Americans, Resettlement Bulletin, April 1943 - April 1946 (File 1)
  - Japanese-American Relations Committee, Information Bulletin, March 1942-February 1946 (File 1)
  - Friends of the American Way, 3 newsletters, undated (File 1)
  - Pastoral Letter to All Friends of Oriental American Peace and Justice newsletter, May 24, 1940 (File 1)
  - Japan Friends' News, newsletter, undated (File 1)
  - California Fellowship of Reconciliation, newsletter, April 2, 1943 (File 1)
- Relocation of Japanese American students materials (Box 1)
  - Gordon Hirabayashi Defense Committee, 1 letter, April 16, 1943 (File 1)
  - National Japanese American Student Relocation Council, minutes of meetings, reports, etc., September and October, 1943 (File 1)
  - Reprint of article on relocation of American-Japanese Students from the Journal of the Association of Collegiate Registrars, April, 1943 (File 1)
  - Printed list of Educational Institutions Attended by Relocated Students, undated (File 1)
  - Printed (private) Directory of American Students of Japanese Ancestry in Schools of Higher Education (File 1)
  - Printed Study of Vocational Experiences of University of California Alumni of Japanese Ancestry (File 1)
  - Application form for employment (File 1)
  - Report of an incident of possible discrimination against a relocated nurse (File 1)
  - National Student Relocation Council, newsletters and progress reports, a series of copies of relocation applications sent to the War Relocation Authority by MSEC on behalf of individual students, July 1942 - February 1943 (File 1)
- Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  envelope of undated California newspaper clippings and items from the following newspapers and magazines: Baltimore Sun, Collier's, Yankee Army Weekly, Honolulu Star-Bulletin, San Francisco Chronicle, Palo Alto Times, New World-Sun Daily, Japanese American News, The Utah Nippo, The Progressive (Madison, Wisconsin), The Woodland Democrat, The Home Front Commando, The Civil Liberties Quarterly and The American Civil Liberties Union News (September, 1942 - March, 1945), The Pacific Citizen (several editions), The Newell Star, The Manzanar Free Press, The Santa Anita Pacemaker (several editions), and The Granada Pioneer (several editions)
  [This collection is so diverse that it defies any useful organization. The Home Front Commando is a good illustration of violently anti-Japanese sentiment. The camp publications from Manzanar, Santa Anita, Granada, and Newell and the American Civil Liberties Union articles are particularly interesting.]
- personal letters and papers (Box 1)
  - to George Tolson from N. Kodaira; Japanese in Seattle, Washington, March, 1942 (File 1)
  - to Kiss Nichols from Mr. Chiura Obata; acknowledgement of reciept of gifts, June 18, 1942 (File 1)
  - to Mrs. Duveneck from Peggy Hayes AFSC business, June 24, 1942 (File 1)
  - to Mr. C. Obata from unknown; reply, July 1, l942 (File 1)
  - to Dr. R. Jones from George New; religious education in evacuation centers, July 2, 1942 (File 1)
  - to Dr. J. Carpenter from unknown; education in evacuation centers, Jan. 19, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Dr. R. Jones from unknown; recommendation for Miss Helen, Feb. 1, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Friends Meeting House Rhoda Dickinson; a gift of $15.36, July 23, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Mr. Bryant from Mrs. E. Pendleton; a collection of clippings accompanied letter, Aug. 3, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Rhoda Dickinson from Mrs. D Duveneck; acknowledgement of gift of July 23, 1943, Aug. 12, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Mrs. Van Wormer from Mrs. Duveneck; correspondence on relocation in East, Aug. 13, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Mrs. Duveneck from Frank Osasa; personal letter, Aug. 22, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Mrs. Duveneck from unknown; regarding Miss T. Washino, Sept. 18, 1943 (File 1)
  - to unknown father from unknown son; printed reproduction of letter from a Nisei soldier, Nov. 20, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Mrs. Duveneck from Yukiko Suzuki; personal letter, Nov. 21, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Mrs. Duveneck from James Azuma; personal letter, Dec. 23, 1943 (File 1)
  - to Miss Duveneck from Mr. and Mrs. H. Hida; personal letter, Jan. 3, 1944 (File 1)
  - to Mrs. Duveneck from Tak Matsui; personal letter, Jan. 19, 1944 (File 1)
  - to Miss Duveneck from Violet Takeshita; personal letter, Jan. 21, 1944 (File 1)
  - to Miss Duveneck from D. Asano; personal letter, Jan. 22, 1944 (File 1)
  - to Mrs. Duveneck from Amy Yamanihi; personal letter, Feb. 4, 1944 (File 1)
  - to Miss Duveneck from Grace Tanabe; personal letter, Feb. 16, 1944 (File 1)
  - Commentary on radio discussion, Aug. 29, 1944. (File 1)
    Question: What to do with the Japanese now in the internment camps in America and whether or not they should be allowed to return to the Pacific Coast. The questions were asked to young children in San Francisco
  - to Mrs. Duveneck from Esther Rhoads; poem written by Idella Stone, Dec. 2, 1944 (File 1)
  - Dramatic reading by Dave Tatsuno, Topaz High School, December 22, 1944 (File 1)
  - two Christmas cards (File 1)
- Pamphlets and reprints (File 2)
  [This collection of pamphlets and reprints is an excellent source of materials for a wide variety of research projects.It is a useful index to the activities of many organizations seeking to educate various sectors of their communities on the question of Japanese Americans during wartime.]
  - published by the WRA (File 2)
    - Questions and Answers for Evacuees (File 2)
    - Pertinent Facts about Relocation Centers and Japanese-Americans (File 2)
    - New Neighbors Among Us (File 2)
    - Relocation of Japanese-Americans (File 2)
    - Relocation Communities for Wartime (File 2)
    - Evacuees Challenge to Democracy (File 2)
    - Relocating a People (File 2)
    - Making Democracy Work (File 2)
  - Publications from Relocation Centers (File 2)
    - The Japanese Evacuation and the Minority Problem (Heart Mountain) (File 2)
    - Christmas Collection of Prose and Poetry (Poston) (File 2)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets from a wide variety of sources (File 2)
    - Fellowship of Reconciliation (File 2)
    - various church groups, including Colorado Council of Churches (File 2)
    - American Friends Service Committee (File 2)
    - The Committee for Resettlement of Japanese-Americans National Japanese American Student Relocation Council Citizens Committee for Resettlement Post War World Council University of Chicago Roundtable, and University of California Roundtable (File 2)
    - Universities Committee on Post-Jar International Problems (File 2)
    - Japanese American Citizens League (File 2)
    - Pacific Coast Committee on American Principle and Fair Play (File 2)
    - Territorial Emergency Service Committees (File 2)
  - reprints of various articles about Japanese-Americans from sources such as The Commonweal, Readers Digest, and other publications (File 2)
  - Copies of True Comics, Nippon to America, The Bussei Life (File 2)
- War Relocation Authority (WRA) and Congressional reports (File 2)
  - The Japanese Question, a speech by Senator Homer T. Bone of Washington. Senate, September 10, 1942 (File 2)
  - Segregation of Loyal and Disloyal Japanese in Relocation Centers, a message from President Roosevelt, September 14, 1943 (File 2)
  - Report, Second Territorial Conference-Morale and Emergency Service Committees, July 21-23, 1944 (File 2)
- Miscellaneous materials (File 2)
  - Kagawa Calendar, 1939 (File 2)
  - The California Civic Unity Call for Immediate Action, September 16, 1946 (File 2)
  - "Religion and Economics" by Toyohiko Kagawa, 1929 from Labour Speaks for Itself on Religion (File 2)
  - Miscellaneous War Relocation Authority (WRA) materials: policy statements, definitions of functions and duties, clarification of facts concerning camp life, protest incidents, and accidents, speeches by WRA officials; WRA position on Japanese American loyalty, and other materials (File 2)
  - 2 sheets of "a review of West Coast newspaper items in the past month ending July 15 and indicating attitude." (File 2)
  - copies of public statements by Joseph Grew, the Honolulu Police Department, the Chief of Military Information in Hawaii, and J. Edgar Hoover on the loyalty of Japanese Americans (File 2)
  - resolutions adopted by various organizations concerning Japanese Americans copies of newspaper articles, radio editorials, etc. concerning the records of Nisei soldiers and the loyalty of Japanese Americans (File 2)
  - Newsletter from "Conference between Americans of Occidental and Oriental Ancestry", January 13, 1941 (File 2)
  - Forum on Japanese Americans in the Victory program, undated (File 2)
  - C.P.M. Information for members and prospects (File 2)
  - "The United States- Japan Conflict" by Bertram Pickard, December 8, 1941 (File 2)
- Notebooks of miscellaneous materials on Japanese Americans during the initial months of World War II (Box 3)
  - Notebook, December 194l-February 1942 (File 3)
    Contains a summary of Proclamations of President of the U.S. Dec 7, and 18, 1941 and Jan 14, 1942; newspaper clippings; minutes of meetings and reports of the American Friends Service Committee; one copy (January 1942) of Current Life, a national Nesei magazine; correspondence with Mrs. Duveneck (includes Esther B. Rhodes letter, March 3, 1942); minutes of a meeting of the Immigrant Serving Agencies of the Community Chest of San Francisco Information; bulletins of the Japanese American Relations Committee; a Plan for Government Sponsored Farm and Craft Resettlement for People of Japanese Parentage, proposed by a member of a Nisei organization; report to and from Raymond Booth; Letter from Lincoln Kanai Dec 1941; NRS Bulletin Feb 20, 1942; FBI Raid in Mountain View Feb 21, 1942; questionnaire for resettlement; Presidential Proclamation #2526 Dec 15, 1942; statement from Mike Masaoka Jan 7, 1942; discussion of Japanese Situation at Executive Committee meeting Feb 7; Committee of Immigrant Serving Agencies minutes Jan 30, 1942; and statement Received from Mike Masaoka Jan 7, 1942
  - Notebook, March 1942 (File 3)
    Contains miscellaneous materials about the first few months of the war and the decision to evacuate Japanese Americans. The materials included are newspaper clippings (primarily from Bay Area newspapers), magazine articles, American Friends Service Committee Bulletins, and personal letters.
  - Notebook, April 1942 (File 3)
    Contains miscellaneous materials concerned primarily with the initial months of evacuation. The materials include newspaper clippings, pamphlets, American Friends Service Committee Bulletins, personal letters (some giving impressions of assembly centers), and magazine articles.
  - Miscellaneous materials (File 3)
    The folder includes: one brief program sheet of a Brotherhood Pageant at Tule Lake; one sheet published by the Denver and Colorado Councils of Churches criticizing anti-Japanese American hate propaganda; a four-page collection of statistics on relocated students; a three-page outline of the staff and program of the Tanforan Camp Art School; minutes of meetings of the American Friends Service Committee; and two unidentifiable fragments of reports
- Notebooks of miscellaneous materials, May-December, l942 (Box 4)
  - Notebook, May 1942 (File 4)
    Articles: report of San Francisco Friends Center May 9-June 8, 1942; Wartime Civil Control Administration May 1942; excerpts from Letters from Japanese Evacuees May 25, 1942; American Friends Service Committee Bulletins May 1942; Public Affairs News Service Bulletin No. VI May 12; The People Nobody Wants; Evacuation by H.V. and M.M. Nicholson, National Refugee Service; special information bulletin, Tanforan: Report on Conditions in Camp as of May 9, 1942; Japanese Evacuation Reports, #4, 11, 12, Have We Forgotten Justice? by Caleb Foote, Newspaper clippings, and letters to Mrs. Duveneck, to Homer Morris May 25, 1942, from Fred H. May 6, 1942, from Grace May 19, 1942, and to Walter Homan May 30, 1942
  - Notebook, June-August 1942 (File 4)
    Contains clippings and assorted materials contain a good deal of information on the initial problems of evacuation and the relocation centers. Among the highlights are: Annual Report of the American Civil Liberties Union(June 1941-June 1942) publications of the Fellowship of Reconciliation National Student Relocation Council; miscellaneous correspondence and reports of the Pacific Coast American Friends Service Committee, including a personal account of a visit with Gordon Hirabayashi; Justice for the Evacuees June 10, 1942; Moving the West-Coast Japanese Article undated; Special Release on Japanese Evacuation Test Case July 20, 1942; Report on Minandoka Relocation Project, ID Aug 1 and Tulelake Relocation Center, CA Aug 3
  - Notebook, September-December 1942 (File 4)
    The material includes: miscellaneous correspondence with Mrs. Duveneck [the lengthier typewritten letters from people within the relocation centers are quite informative]; newspaper clippings; Japanese American Relocation Committee Information Bulletins; one copy of Survey Graphic (Sept. 1942), a magazine of social interpretation; Fellowship of Reconciliation Newsletter and publication Outcasts!; a copy of a speech by Bradford Smith before the Japanese American Committee for Democracy In New York (December 6, 1942); picture of Heart Mountain in Wyoming; article from "The Christian Century" Nov. 18, 1942; The Resettlement of American-Born Japanese by George E. Rundquist Oct. 28; Remember Pearl Harbor meeting Dec. 6, 1942; The Guns of Toulon Nov. 27, 1942
- Notebooks, l943-l944 (Box 5)
  - Notebook, January-June 1943 (File 5)
    Contains materials about l)life in the relocation centers and 2)the enlistment of Japanese Americans in the armed forces. The materials included are primarily newspaper clippings and bulletins of the American Friends Service Committee.
  - Notebook, July-December 1943 (File 5)
    Miscellaneous collection of materials dealing with 1) Japanese American soldiers and 2)problems at the Tule Lake center in November 1943.
  - Notebook, 1943-1944 (File 5)
    Contains assorted issues of the following three publications: War Relocation Authority newsletters', July 26, 1943-Nov. 22, 1943, Japanese American Committee for Democracy newsletters, Feb. 1943-Jan. 1944, and Resettlement Bulletin, Sept. 1943-June 1944
  - Notebook, 1944 (File 5)
    Contains miscellaneous newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and newsletters of various organizations. [much of the material is duplicated elsewhere in the collection]. Among the highlights of the notebook are: Japanese American Relations Committee Information Bulletins, a publication describing Amache, and a copy of the Far Eastern Survey.
  - File of articles, circa 1944 (File 5)